Peyton Conway March Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Peyton Conway March Papers 1897-1955 (bulk 1898-1933)
MSS31302
March, Peyton Conway
6,500 items
18 containers plus 11 oversize
11 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Army officer and Chief of Staff of the Army during and after World War I. Correspondence, reports, military training manuals, book and article drafts, lectures and speeches, notebooks, news clippings, printed matter, scrapbooks, and other papers relating to March's military career.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937--Correspondence.; Bliss, Tasker Howard, 1853-1930--Correspondence.; Graves, William Sidney, 1865-1940--Correspondence.; MacArthur, Arthur, Jr., 1845-1912.; March, Peyton Conway, 1864-1955.; March, Peyton Conway, 1864-1955. Nation at war. 1932.; March, Peyton Conway, Jr., 1896-1918.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948 My experiences in the World War. 1931.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948--Correspondence.
Organizations
Army War College (U.S.); Japan. Rikugun.; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; United States. Army. Artillery.; United States. Army. Astor Battery.; United States. Department of the Army. General Staff.
Subjects
Air bases--California--Riverside.; Artillery drill and tactics.; Artillery.; Eastern question (Far East); Military bases--Kansas.; Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905--Manchuria (China); Spanish-American War, 1898--Philippines.; World War, 1914-1918--France.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
China--Foreign relations--Japan.; Fort Riley (Kan.)--History.; Japan--Foreign relations--China.; March Air Force Base (Calif.); Philippines--History--Philippine American War, 1899-1902.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.
Occupations
Army officers.
Provenance
The papers of Peyton Conway March, military officer and army chief of staff, were given to the Library of Congress by Peyton Conway March, Cora McEntee March, and Lawrence Martin, 1952-1958.
Transfers
When the papers were re-processed in 2015, items were transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs were transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division and maps to Geography and Map Division where they are identified as part of the Peyton Conway March Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Peyton Conway March are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1864, Dec. 27 Born, Easton, Penn.
1880 1884 Student, Lafayette College, Easton, Penn.
1888 Graduate, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.; Commissioned second lieutenant and assiged to the 3rd United States Artillery.
1891 Married Josephine Smith Cunningham (died 1904)
1894 Promoted to first lieutenant, assigned to the 5th United States Artillery
1896 1898 Attended the Artillery School at Fort Monroe, Hampton, Va.
1898 Organized and designated captain of the Astor Battery
1898 1899 Commander, Astor Battery, Spanish-American War, Philippines campaign and the capture of Manila
1899 Aide to General Arthur MacArthur; promoted to major, 33rd Volunteer Infantry, Philippine American War
1900 1901 Provincial governor and commissary of prisoners, Philippines
1901 1903 Reverted to regular army captain; commanded the 19th Battery, Field Artillery, Fort Riley, Kans.
1903 1907 Member, War Department General Staff
1904 Military observer, Japanese Army, Russo-Japanese War
1907 Promoted to major
1907 1911 Member, Artillery Board; commander, 1st Battalion, 6th Field Artillery
1911 1916 Adjutant, successive appointments by the adjutant general to Fort Riley, the Department of the Missouri, the Central Department, the 2nd Division, and department headquarters in Washington, D.C.
1916 Promoted to colonel
1916 1917 Commander, 8th Field Artillery on the Mexican border
1917 Promoted to brigadier general in June and placed in command of the 1st Field Artillery Brigade, 1st Division, American Expeditionary Forces; in August, promoted to major general in the National Army and placed in command of the First army and nondivisional artillery, American Expeditionary Forces; in September, appointed to the General Staff and promoted to major general in the regular army
1918 1921 Chief of staff, United States Army. Established the leading role of the chief of staff in the army hierarchy; directed the buildup of American forces in Europe; centralized control of supplies; created the Air Service, Tank Corps, and Chemical Warfare Service; and oversaw demobilization at the end of World War I
1921 Retired as a major general in November
1923 Married Cora V. McEntee (died 1964)
1930 Advanced to general on the retired list
1955, Apr. 13 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Peyton Conway March (1864-1955) span the years 1897-1955, with the bulk of the material dating from 1898 to 1933. The papers are organized into the following series: Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Miscellany, Scrapbooks, and Oversize. The collection is focused on March's globe-spanning military career, specializing in artillery command, and his retirement writings and opinions on military topics. March is given credit for establishing the primacy of the chief of staff position within the army hierarchy. As chief of staff, March succeeded in transporting the troops and supplies to Europe for the rapid buildup of the American Expeditionary Forces in 1918 and then overcame the logistical challenge of demobilization in 1919. Notable correspondents in the papers include Newton Diehl Baker, Tasker Howard Bliss,William Sidney Graves, and John J. Pershing.
The Correspondence series has a chronological file from 1911 to 1955 and a small alphabetical file that dates solely from 1918 to 1921, while March was chief of staff. The correspondence is largely military-related before 1921, the year of his retirement. Post retirement correspondence concerns his writing projects, special requests from the public, and personal correspondence with friends, often other retired military personnel.
The Speeches and Writings file includes the drafts of his 1932 book The Nation at War, March's personal history of World War I and a critical response to Pershing's 1931 book My Experiences in the World War. Book reviews and related material are also included. Additionally, this series contains copies of lectures before the Army War College, speeches, newspaper articles, and draft writings on the Astor Battery, his memoirs, and his thoughts on Japanese intentions in Asia in 1933.
The Subject File is largely organized around March's various military assignments: command of artillery at Fort Riley, Kansas, command of the Astor Battery in the Philippines during the Spanish-American War, service in the Philippines working with General Arthur MacArthur during the 1899 Philippine American War, assignment to the Japanese Imperial Army in Manchuria as an observer during the Russo-Japanese War, and service in France during World War I. Also in the Subject File are reports and training manuals on a variety of army topics, but with a special focus on World War I and on artillery. March's memorandum arguing against the Siberian intervention by Allied forces in 1918 is in the Subject File; correspondence concerning the Siberian intervention is in the Correspondence File.
The Miscellany series is primarily composed of news clippings and printed matter related to March, an assortment of War Department proposals and reports, and other miscellaneous material.
The Scrapbooks series, all placed in Oversize, has nine volumes, seven of which are collections of newspaper clippings, with a few photographs and magazine articles, documenting the career of March. The last two scrapbooks relate to March Air Force Base, Riverside, California, which was named for March's son, Peyton C. March, Jr., an army air corps pilot who was killed in a 1918 flight training exercise in Texas.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Correspondence File, 1900-1955
Speeches and Writings, 1918-1954
Subject File, 1897-1955
Miscellany, 1900-1955
Scrapbooks, 1898-1951
Oversize, 1898-1951
Container List
- Correspondence File, 1900-1955 (Box 1-6)
  Letters sent and received..
  Arranged in a chronological file and a small personal file organized alphabetically by name of person or organization.
  - Chronological file (Box 1)
    - 1900-1930, (20 folders)
    - 1931, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1932
      - Jan.-Sept., (5 folders)
      - Oct.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1933, (4 folders)
    - 1934
      - Jan.-Apr.
      - May-Dec., (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1935-1936, (4 folders)
    - 1937-1955, (19 folders) (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 6)
  - Personal file, A-Y, 1918-1921, (20 folders)
- Speeches and Writings, 1918-1954 (Box 6-9)
  Drafts and other material relating to March's book The Nation at War, lectures, many given at the United States Military Academy, speeches, drafts of writings, articles, letters to the editor, and some writings by others.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of writing or title.
  - Annual lectures before the Army War College, 1931-1938, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - "The Astor Battery," undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - "Japanese Strategy in the Far East," 1933
  - Memoir drafts, undated
  - Miscellaneous lectures and speeches, 1929-1937, undated, (3 folders)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 1918, 1926-1928, 1938-1944, undated, (2 folders)
  - The Nation at War (Box 8)
    - Book reviews, 1932-1933
    - Drafts, circa 1931, (8 folders)
    - Financial records, 1931-1946 (Box 9)
    - Serial proofs 1-7, circa 1932
  - Newspaper articles and letters to the editor, 1926, 1932, 1944, 1954
  - Writings by others, 1921-1925, 1943-1944, undated
- Subject File, 1897-1955 (Box 9-15)
  Material relating to March's military service, including his service in the Philippines, at Fort Riley, Kansas, in World War I, and also his time with the Japanese Imperial Army during the Russo-Japanese war. Includes reports, military training manuals, orders, military correspondence and memoranda, and biographical material.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Army School, 1915-1916 (Box 9)
  - Artillery, reports, 1903-1907, undated
  - Biographical material, circa 1917-circa 1953
  - Desert Rock, 1952
  - Fort Riley, Kans.
    - Diary, circa 1908-circa 1911
    - Field artillery board notebook, 1908-1910 (Box 10)
    - Report of Major George V. Read, 1910 See also Oversize, (2 folders)
    - Reports, 1903-1908
  - Funeral and obituaries, 1955
  - Horoscope, 1915
  - Military demobilization, United States history of, 1950
    - Chapters 1-3, (2 folders)
    - Chapter 3 notes-Chapter 4 (Box 11)
  - Military training and instructional manuals
    - 1897, 1911-1917, (5 folders)
    - 1917-1918, undated, (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - Philippines
    - Astor Battery
      - Clothing and material issued, circa 1898 See Oversize
      - Muster roll showing discharge, 2 Feb. 1899 See Oversize
      - Recruitment and organization, 1898
    - Chronological file, 1898-1906, (2 folders)
    - Military supplies, 1898-1899, undated, (5 folders) (Box 13)
    - Reports of the United States Military government of the Philippines
      - 1901, (2 folders)
      - 1903 (Box 14)
    - Villamor, Blás and Juan, circa 1898
  - Russo-Japanese War
    - Chronological file, 1904-1906, (2 folders)
    - Lecture: "Observations on the Russo-Japanese War," 1905
    - Miscellany, undated
    - Motieling Pass, report and enclosures, 1904 See also Oversize
    - Notebooks, 1904
      - Books 1-8, (4 folders)
      - Books 9 and unnumbered, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - "Notes on Manchuria," circa 1900-circa 1904
  - Siberian intervention, 1918
  - Volunteer army, proposed legislation, 1905, undated
  - World War I, 1916-1918, (4 folders)
- Miscellany, 1900-1955 (Box 16-18)
  News clippings, printed matter, War Department proposals and reports, notes, small notebooks, and some photographs.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Congressional Record, 1920, 1932, 1938, 1947-1955 (Box 16)
  - Diary and pocket books, circa 1890-circa 1935
  - Invitations and cards, circa 1930-1953
  - Lists of names, unidentified, undated
  - News clippings, 1918-1955 See also Oversize, (3 folders)
  - Notes, undated
  - Photographs of gravestones and unidentified aerial views, undated, See also Oversize
  - Printed matter, 1900-1937, 1953-1954, undated See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - Statements before Congress, 1935
  - War Department proposals and reports
    - "Development of the Four Army Organization," 1933
    - Miscellaneous, 1905-1906, 1926
    - "Statistical Data Relative to Port Army Supply Bases," 1919 (Box 18)
    - Transportation service, 1919
- Scrapbooks, 1898-1951
  Nine scrapbooks primarily containing newspaper clippings and some photographs and articles concerning the military career of March. The last two scrapbooks contain photographs and text pertaining to March Air Force Base, Riverside County, Calif., which was named after March's son, an army air corps pilot killed in a training flight in 1918.
  Arranged chronologically See Oversize
- Oversize, 1898-1951 (Box OV 1-OV 11)
  Maps, muster roll, printed matter, photographs, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Subject File (Box OV 1)
    - Fort Riley, Kans.
      - Report of Major George V. Read, eight maps, 1910 (Container 10)
    - Philippines
      - Astor Battery
        - Clothing and material issued, circa 1898 (Container 12)
        - Muster roll showing discharge 2 Feb. 1899 (Container 12) (Box OV 2)
    - Russo-Japanese War
      - Motieling Pass, report and enclosures, two maps, 1904 (Container 14)
      - "Notes on Manchuria," map "Disposition of the Russian Divisions," Aug.-Sept. 1904 (Container 14)
  - Miscellany
    - News clippings, article on canvas, 1918 (Container 16)
    - Photographs of unidentified aerial views, undated (Container 16)
    - Printed matter, portrait, undated (Container 17)
  - Scrapbooks, 1898-1951 (Container 18) (Box OV 3)
    - 1898
    - 1918 (Box OV 4)
    - 1918-1919 (Box OV 5)
    - 1918-1921, 1941 (Box OV 6)
    - 1919-1926 (Box OV 7)
    - Clippings about The Nation at War, 1932 (Box OV 8)
    - 1943-1951 (Box OV 9)
    - March Air Force Base, California, 1951 (Box OV 10)
    - Medal of Honor Ceremony at March Air Force Base, 1951 (Box OV 11)